Right, so this particular part of the series is about just the consolidation apex continued, really.
What we're going to really focus on is the retest, and whereabouts the shelf can turn up.
It can be far away from prices, and be close to the apex, and that really will kind of determine what kind of response, okay, what kind of characteristics we can expect at the high, what's likely to happen when the shelf is further away from price, etc.
But really, just going into it.
what we're looking at the apex is of course price slowing down then having a pop to find some liquidity now this is the most important part okay once the high is in the high has to hold okay so if we're going to go short i like to go short of the first touch anyway okay that's the highest probability for me
ultimately when do you get that pop okay we're starting to see liquidity in drain okay so the shelf when price is popping out of it is further draining the inventory of liquidity and generally at the high you're going to get jump
price action okay for this range it can be more sustained than the higher timeframes
but it will largely look quite jumpy as well now depending on how far the shelf is away from the
apex okay it will help us differentiate between whether this retest is likely to go all the way
back higher towards the high especially if there's unfil liquidity left inside the shelf okay
like the top's not the top's already been picked there's liquidity left at the bottom
and sometimes in those cases we'll come grab the bottom and we will go to new highs to look for a better unfilled pocket of the quality it's just part of the game that'll be our pain trade you have to you know what we will see on the lower time frame generally as well is price build up okay it'll build up to absorb this high and then shoot and it's in this anatomy which doesn't fit the parameters of a high because what we like to see our high is weaker and weaker and weaker rallies absorbing the shelf the high holding okay
most of the time as well once you get into this part once you poked beneath the apex base
price shouldn't okay very very often winning trades really on the winning successful highs
it shouldn't materially push back into the apex it might do our later time down the line
and that's where we get into the broader shelf okay holding the higher time frame price swing
we'll have a look at in a minute but as and when it's breaking down is we're anticipating a
a lack of by side, okay, a dryness or weakness on the by side,
depending on the weight price run up and then how it released
and also how the apex base slash the lower time frame shelf was flipped.
At this point it is quite important to note there's numerous shelves, okay?
You can have a five-minute shelf, which is going to be right at the highest, okay?
It's going to be right around here.
You can have a one-hour shelf which is holding the overall broader apex up,
and then you can have the higher time frame shell which can be like you know a bit further away
from price okay now when price is breaking down through this let's say h1 shell okay um
what we're going to start to see is price pick up some feeding fractal you know by that point
there has been pretty much a momentum shift and it would generally draw back in
to this liquidity base that is forming and there we might actually get
shelf flip trade that's what I call the shelf flip trade so here's your
shelf a very key parameter inside there there needs to be a accumulation which
push past the base of the apex and you know price draws back into it or it
draws back into it there we can go short that's the kind of self I look for but
the most important thing at that point in time is this level that price is
picking up is feeding a higher time frame of big thick level of liquidity
into price on into the cell side and also you know the way price extended higher
there's going to be certain kind of structures inside there where the shelf is
washed already the run is getting weak it's jumpy which further substantiates the
correct characteristics of a high okay but a very key parameter is the high
holes once we get beneath the shell okay you can get the we can have the retest
there's some unfil liquidity left around the apex base and once we get beneath
the apex base we can draw back into it but it shouldn't really spend a lot
time and you know one of these accumulations will give us quite a lot of responses or quite
good responses but again it's important to note here as well the more you engage with these
specific features of a high the specific feature of a price swing sorry the highs the shelves the
liquidity base the point and release the clean breaking point um price gap slipping through inefficient
legs that's all going to kind of build your understanding and build um
Yeah, so it's going to build your understanding on how to trade the different variations actually how to spot these different variations
You know you can become more effective at finding them
But let's have a look at a quick example when a shelf is close to the apex base
Okay, so this is pound you are still at one minute right price shoots there's a characteristic of high
It's actually picking up a decent level. It's extending by its highs
You know there's a few principles that we're looking at here the further price runs the weaker it gets extensions get filled
there's an extension the further price run the weaker against and of course inefficient
price action inefficient legs are vulnerable so they will be my first touch sure okay now in
this case here we see a few clusters hugging price okay but really what's happening here is as
price went along it was picking up the bulk of liquidity so in real terms the bulk of liquidity in
any price one would be here the fact that price picks up a nice level
then invalidates the shell okay poking beneath it is the first good sign that uh this you know
that the by side is running weak okay had to dig this far or this far to find buyers okay in many
many instances it's fine enough buyers here if it was going to continue if we just was a normal
price pause it would find enough buyers here to continue would maintain this structure okay
will maintain that structure now that is going to that is going to materially push price back
down here it could easily reach down here build up okay and it's our job to spot that scene of
examples spot that the momentum is shifting back on the buy side because it's found some residual
liquidity here and it could come right back to the high and draw down but that's not what we're
looking at here so in this case the shelf is very close to price okay here's your like your one
mini apex the tick chart apex so also what i'd make the know of here is when you have a price
like this you can have a very small fractal apex consolidation so this is a price swing right here to here to
here this inside here there'd be a fractal apex and of course this is a broader apex when the
fractal apex breaks down okay we're not actually going to go and say oh this is going to materially
break down 5 000 pips at the downside we still have this to contend with and once you get through
that and the broader apex breaks down that's when you've got more of a profound
shift in the state of liquidity same and that is when you have to then
consider if the shelf is far away from price or is actually holding right
close to the broader apex okay but in this case like there's your one minute
apex or you tick chart apex here's your one minute apex price and validates
the sorry here's your one minute show price and validates the shell comes
draws back up this inefficient extension like okay so that
the way price extended they left it vulnerable comes and consumes whatever liquidity is left
inside this feeder draws back up this uh the way price extended down right then again takes another
run clearing up the liquidity here or picking up whatever liquidity is there and this time because
this kind of stops in the middle of nowhere price does and there's a void of liquidity there
price does end up ripping right to the apex right into the high okay and that's a very
consistent feature in price you're going to see that time and time and time again price coming back
into the apex that is the most worrisome part but at that point in time what we're relying on
is the shift in the state of liquidity the price behavior has changed we've deviated beneath the
inventory of buyers the inventory is where the full color buyers are if price gets past them the buyers are
okay few things can happen price can sustain a range and then build up and go through the top that's a
price pause, it can of course break down and seek liquidity at the core base, the core
inventory of that broader price run.
When are we likely to get price pauses and price going to maintain the range and then push
to new highs, when these are picking up midflow residual levels, okay?
Now in this case, what happens is, you know, the way price run up from here to here, that
is a price run in and of itself, so there's going to be some liquidity left over, you
know it again forms a fractal apex there okay so you see the high it comes into the
shelf weak rally and then they invalidate some kind of apex comes right back to the high
and then you see weak on weaker rallies until this apex gives out and it draws right back
down it picks up some feeding fractal here on the tick chart I'm sure it would it
draws right up that extension leg this time into the apex base area and again
because the same thing over and over once you get past this low you actually see prices
accelerate through this inefficient leg. Volatility is a function of liquidity. So if there's
a thin level of liquidity here, really important to know this, understand this. If there's a thin
area, okay, an exposed area of liquidity inside here, we can expect price to trend through it or
kind of gap slip through it. But then what that means is because this is now extending
it efficiently this leg is getting weaker and weaker and weaker and weaker all it needs is a small
bulk area of liquidity a residual level is enough because of the way price extended down it's extending
down because this is a void of liquidity the way price is extending out the weaker and weaker is
getting and here it's meeting it you know just a residual mass of buyers and that results in a price
response okay so if you're going to trade counter flow you know you'll see you'll see you
some kind of, there's very clear parameters for when we're going to actually engage counter flows,
when we're going to look for residual levels to give big responses, and when we're not.
But again, the way price extended down, picked up a decent mass, and then it goes on a run right back higher.
These levels were picked up, picked up, this is a feeder, you see a response, and then, of course,
we just go to the top side of this level, okay?
again this is forming an apex here okay price plummets through the apex comes and
picks up a shelf which is a bit further than price this time and that actually
gives it because price came all this way down to find the shelf when it picks up
some residual liquidity or the remaining inventory inside of the shelf of this
price from okay that's the price one individual price one the way price
extend it down beneath the apex it left itself vulnerable for price to draw right back to the apex
base for a retest and of course we're going to integrate a clean breaking point here as well now when you
have a small apex consolidation like this what like five pips three pips four pips we can generally
you know draw the clean breaking point and we can take a response of the clean breaking point because
this can have a stream of cell side liquidity inside there it's only when you have a bigger fractal a higher
time frame fractal they're actually looking to pinpoint the individual
components of that particular base just so first of all you know we can
refine our levels define our risk no get higher our probability but also on
the higher time frame apex consolidations which we're going to look at probably
in the next video each one of these features inside of the higher time frame
consolidation you know it's going to have more liquidity inside of those
individual features at the point released the liquidity top the clean breaking
point the liquidity bottom base or bottom side of the liquidity base but again so it
has to travel a bit further to find liquidity inside the shell because of the
way it extended into it in this case it wouldn't be surprising if price came
right to this high the top side it wouldn't be surprising if price run right
to here okay and these are scenarios we have to consider these are scenarios
you know that you have to engage with time and time and time again to basically be able to
anticipate one of the other happening a lot of the times you're going to be right the first time
okay so a lot a lot of the times you're just going to take that short it's going to go straight
to profit and you know you're going to catch a jet to Africa as come by it but sometimes
pain trades occur and price will go against you and that's why we have it I have a personal
to trade limit and execute trades of particular self by that point look at the overall
price ring apex sorry liquidity base price pause continuation leg shelf high apex base and then
digs deep no low comes for apex base retest goes in a price one clears out the inventory
or sorry the residual liquidity at this base runs it and deals it off picks up more sellers
again it doesn't really respond off these two levels because they already picked up it does
respond on the feeder here okay you can see it but that is just coming right back down
it's basically a price pause okay there's not enough liquidity inside it's a stock price
until it comes to the top of that kind of swing now by that point we're in a range okay
sellers are pushing on price if shifted okay buyers can't continue and you know this is a residual
level so we would be anticipating for price to continue down and again this can be very
difficult you know this is a kind of a dirty high there's a very clean high that's a very clean
high that's a very clean high that's a very clean high and sometimes the broader price swings
because on broader price wings there's going to be more liquidity hugging one side of the market
you know you can't have some more volatility as well okay but same applies so price
those end up coming right to where the point of release okay it extends past lows the
the trail of inefficiency again it clusters as well a bit but yeah comes to the point
of release on this fractal who takes another run at eyes okay and this time it doesn't respond
here though it does respond there actually but it doesn't kind of sell off from there what
it does is it goes to the unfilled liquidity okay it goes to the unfilled liquidity on this fractal
easy again could have gone to the top side okay it's just part of the game now in this case we
have another example of a shelf very very very close to the apex base and i'll get and again
we're on the one minute chart okay so this apex space is visible on the tick charts price breaks
through it okay look why it does it comes to the only bear of unfilled liquidity let's take a zoom in
if we can okay cool you see that wick uh you see that wick so price punks
comes right back down to pick up, the only one full liquidity inside here would be this,
the bottom side then, flips the apex base, or it breaks the apex base,
comes back down to grab the last bare one field liquidity inside this shelf,
comes to where for apex base retest, okay? And again, the only time I would take this
apex base retest, which we will cover up probably in the next video again,
is it first of all, it's picking up a higher time from level, and then, of course,
the state of liquidity of the run-off has to be weak enough for me to say that is just not enough
buyers left so a better example of this would be if it went all the way down here and then came
back that'll be a better short for me okay because that's further telling me that prices
having to travel further to find buyers when on the way higher it successfully found buyers
very very very very close to it and then the principal comes in the further price runs
they're weaker it gets okay and you know the price goes to the weaker side
In other words, if there's a weakness in buyers here,